<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here is a necessarye treatyse for all maner persons to reade, and hath to name, the Maydens crosse rewe</title>
            <title>Maydens crosse rewe</title>
            <author>Wyer, Robert, fl. 1530-1556.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1540</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121881</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857040</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857040</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22708</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06747)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22708)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 137:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here is a necessarye treatyse for all maner persons to reade, and hath to name, the Maydens crosse rewe</title>
                  <title>Maydens crosse rewe</title>
                  <author>Wyer, Robert, fl. 1530-1556.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Wyer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1540?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end "q[uod] Robert Wyer", on which basis the authorship is sometimes attributed to him; but as he printed the book it may be meant as an imprint.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="didactic_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:22708:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22708:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Here is a neceſſarye Treatyſe for all maner perſons to reade, and hath to name, the Maydens Croſſe rewe.</head>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>IAnus Byfrons, amyddes Ianuary</l>
               <l>With his froſty berde, &amp; thycke loches rore</l>
               <l>Begen the colde calenda<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of February</l>
               <l>Right than I thought, how lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge me before</l>
               <l>My mayſter Lydgate, dyd applye hym ſore</l>
               <l>Fables to fayne vnto moralyte</l>
               <l>To ſhewe the euyll theyr iniquyte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ All this conſyderyd to my bedde I went</l>
               <l>Fallynge a ſlepe than full ryght ſhortly</l>
               <l>And in this ſlumbre me thought incontynent</l>
               <l>By an olyue tre I was full ſodaynely</l>
               <l>Where ſat a Mayde complaynynge rufully</l>
               <l>Beatynge her handes, and vnder bowes dyd ſhrowde</l>
               <l>In the maner folowynge bewaylynge all alowde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22708:2"/>
               <l>¶ Alas ſhe ſayde I may nowe ſorowe euer</l>
               <l>My good frende is gone whiche wolde haue remayne</l>
               <l>The tyme ſo paſt ſe nowe ſhall I neuer</l>
               <l>Therfore no wonder thoughe that I complayne</l>
               <l>With ſyghes depe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd with mortall payne</l>
               <l>My flowrynge age I ſpent in vanyte</l>
               <l>With all wretched foly and fragalyte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ I toke no hede vnto dame reaſon</l>
               <l>Whiche theſe prouerbes folowynge dyd me tell</l>
               <l>Vpon all the letters to haue concluſyon</l>
               <l>So was I ruled by thre enemyes ſo fell</l>
               <l>As the worlde, the fleſſhe, and the fende of hell</l>
               <l>But as I may, I wyll them ſpecify</l>
               <l>Eche after other as I harde them truely.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>A.</head>
               <l>ALas ryot ledeth the brydyll rayne</l>
               <l>Alas that I loued ſo concupyſcence</l>
               <l>Alas tyme paſt may not turne agayne</l>
               <l>Alas that I loſt it by neclygence</l>
               <l>Alas to lernynge I had no dylygence</l>
               <l>Alas that euer I loued vnhappynes</l>
               <l>Alas I haue banyſhed reaſon and ſadnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>B.</head>
               <l>Beware thou youth euermore of ydlenes</l>
               <l>Beware of pryde, and alſo enuy</l>
               <l>Beware of wr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>the, be ruled by mekenes</l>
               <l>Beware of couetuouſnes and of glotony</l>
               <l>Beware alſo of the ſynne of Lechery</l>
               <l>Beware ryght well alſo of preſumpcyon</l>
               <l>Beware and wyſe alſo of falſe rebellyon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22708:2"/>
               <head>C.</head>
               <l>Coueyte heauen with dedes of Charyte</l>
               <l>Coueyte connynge with all thy buſynes</l>
               <l>Coueyte the company of dame fydelyte</l>
               <l>Coueyte wyſdome and all ſtablenes</l>
               <l>Coueyte repentaunce for the wretchednes</l>
               <l>Coueyte meaſure for thy bodely wealthe</l>
               <l>Coueyte the waye alſo of thy ſoules healthe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>D.</head>
               <l>Drede god alſo aboue euery kynge.</l>
               <l>Drede for ſynne euermore the vengeaunce</l>
               <l>Drede for the tyme, the tyme of rekenynge</l>
               <l>Drede for to do thy neyghboure anoyaunce</l>
               <l>Drede aboue other thy ſelfe for to auaunce</l>
               <l>Drede for to do euyll alwaye certayne</l>
               <l>Drede euermore alſo thy ſouerayne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>E.</head>
               <l>Exyle from the falſhode and flatery</l>
               <l>Exyle from the euermore the vycyous</l>
               <l>Exyle alſo vyle ſpeche and rebaudry</l>
               <l>Exyle all thynges nowe ſuperſtycyous</l>
               <l>Exyle dyſdayne whiche is preſumptuous</l>
               <l>Exyle foly and dyſſymulacion</l>
               <l>Exyle alwaye alſo detraccion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>F.</head>
               <l>Folowe the trace of truth and ryghtuouſnes</l>
               <l>Folowe example of vertuous gouernaunce</l>
               <l>Folowe bounte and alſo lowlynes</l>
               <l>Folowe meaſure in all thy purueaunce</l>
               <l>Folowe wyſdome by good remembraunce</l>
               <l>Folowe Iuſtyce without corrupcion</l>
               <l>Folowe conſcyence at euery ſeaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22708:3"/>
               <head>G.</head>
               <l>Gladly be ruled by counceyll prudent</l>
               <l>Gladly enclyne alwayes to reaſon</l>
               <l>Gladly to lerne be thou moche dylygent</l>
               <l>Gladly take tr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uth to thy companyon</l>
               <l>Gladly forſake the yll operacyon</l>
               <l>Gladly ſerue God and thy prynce alſo</l>
               <l>Gladly be pacyent in trouble and wo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>H.</head>
               <l>Haue good reſpect vnto thynges all</l>
               <l>Haue thou no doubte of holy ſcrypture</l>
               <l>Haue God in thy mynde moſt memoryall</l>
               <l>Haue gentyll chere and countenaunce demure</l>
               <l>Haue good remorſe to euery creature</l>
               <l>Haue moſt thy truſt in Goddes goodnes</l>
               <l>Haue not thy truſt in worldely ryches.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>I knewe nothynge in youth what I was</l>
               <l>I wolde not knowe the ſteppes of vertue</l>
               <l>I thought full lytell howe my youth ſholde pas</l>
               <l>I wolde nothynge the carnall vyce exchewe</l>
               <l>I thought good fortune wolde me well renewe</l>
               <l>I was <gap reason="illegible" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed or that I was ware</l>
               <l>I lytell thought of myne after care.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>K.</head>
               <l>Knowe fyrſt God and thy ſelfe ſecondly</l>
               <l>Knowe well thy prynce by dewe obedyence</l>
               <l>Knowe thy neyghboure well and certaynely</l>
               <l>Knowe well connynge by dewe expetyence</l>
               <l>Knowe well in whom thou mayſt haue confydence</l>
               <l>Knowe well the pore and not hym forſake</l>
               <l>Knowe hym well that thou of counſayle make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22708:3"/>
               <head>L.</head>
               <l>Loue God alſo aboue euery thynge</l>
               <l>Loue thy neyghboure and cheryſſhe thy wyfe</l>
               <l>Loue not ryot nor backe reakenynge</l>
               <l>Loue alwaye peace and auoyde the ſtryfe</l>
               <l>Loue in honeſte to lede thy lyfe</l>
               <l>Loue euer myrth and vertuous dyſporte</l>
               <l>Loue to the wofull to gyue ayde and comforte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>M.</head>
               <l>Moche myſchyfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of great debate</l>
               <l>Moche drynke doth wyſdome aſwage</l>
               <l>Moche ſorowe doth the courage abate</l>
               <l>Moche euyll greueth a great outrage</l>
               <l>Moche medlynge letteth great auantage</l>
               <l>Moche Ioye grounded vpon vnyte</l>
               <l>Moche harme doth growe of inſtabylyte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>N.</head>
               <l>Nothynge is ſweter than the dewe of grace</l>
               <l>No man may taſte it, but by Sapyence</l>
               <l>No man without charyte may heauen purchace</l>
               <l>No man without laboure may haue a ſcyence</l>
               <l>Nothynge to man is better than pacyence</l>
               <l>No earthly ryches, but it is tranſmutable</l>
               <l>No man without maners can be conuenable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>O.</head>
               <l>O mortall man ryſe out of deedly ſynne</l>
               <l>O foolyſſhe love of worldly vanyte</l>
               <l>O vnkynde man to amende the bygynne</l>
               <l>O man remembre Goddes benygnyte</l>
               <l>O man Goddes goodnes conſydre and ſe</l>
               <l>O man remembre howe he graunteth ſpace</l>
               <l>O man in tyme nowe take the gyfte of grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22708:4"/>
               <head>P.</head>
               <l>Pleaſe God thy maker, and kepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement</l>
               <l>Pleaſe not thy fleſſhe, by carnall affeccyon</l>
               <l>Pleaſe well thy prynce and be to hym obedyenc</l>
               <l>Pleaſe not the worlde with hole occaſyon</l>
               <l>Pleaſe the cauſer of thy fyrſt creacyon</l>
               <l>Pleaſe not the Deuyll, by Pryde, Enuy, and Ire</l>
               <l>Pleaſe hym aboue, that is the heauenly Empyre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <head>Q.</head>
               <l>Quare deo fui ſic contrarius</l>
               <l>Quare heu non ipſum amaui</l>
               <l>Quare noloiſſem cum habuerim tempus</l>
               <l>Quare ve ſic ſemper peccaui</l>
               <l>Quare mundum ego frequentaui</l>
               <l>Quare me ſequetis o tu vir in vanis</l>
               <l>Quare laboras ſic mundi inanis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>R.</head>
               <l>Ryght greuouſly I haue God offended</l>
               <l>Ryght nought I thought vpon his Iuſtyce</l>
               <l>Ryght lytell I thought for to be a mended</l>
               <l>Ryght oft I dyd my neyghboure preiudyce</l>
               <l>Ryght well I thought fortune ſhulde ſuffyce</l>
               <l>Ryght lytell I thought on my ſoules healthe</l>
               <l>Ryght ſo my mynde was all on worldly wealthe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>S.</head>
               <l>Supporte not wronge vnto ryght contrary</l>
               <l>Supporte Iuſtyce with all thy dylygence</l>
               <l>Supporte not thy ſeruaunt to do vylany</l>
               <l>Supporte no man whan he doth offence</l>
               <l>Supporte alwaye the grounde of Capyence</l>
               <l>Supporte pouerte in the tyme of nede</l>
               <l>Supporte alwaye the ryghtfull man to ſpede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22708:4"/>
               <head>T.</head>
               <l>Truth may be bolde in euery maner of place</l>
               <l>Truth is good and muſt nedes endure</l>
               <l>Truth doth his ſeruaunt call vnto great grace</l>
               <l>Truth is ryght fayre and a precyous treaſure</l>
               <l>Truth is worſhyped of euery creature</l>
               <l>Truth is good both in worde and dede</l>
               <l>Truth of God ſhall haue rewarde and mede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>W.</head>
               <l>Wo worth falſhode nowe euery where aryued</l>
               <l>Wo worth alſo falſe ymagynacyon</l>
               <l>Wo worth pryde whiche hath mekenes depryued</l>
               <l>Wo worth nowe flatery and diſſymulacyon</l>
               <l>Wo worth doublenes and detraceyon</l>
               <l>Wo worth debate without extynguyſſhement</l>
               <l>Wo worth alſo a corrupt Iudgement.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>Xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i time ſemper potentiam</l>
               <l>Xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i vide ac quin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vulnera</l>
               <l>Xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c pete miſericordiam</l>
               <l>Xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i decem ſerua mandata</l>
               <l>Xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i ſit nomen in memoria</l>
               <l>Xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i mors liberet nos a morte</l>
               <l>Xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i nos ſaluet omni ip<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Y.</head>
               <l>Ye that lyſt heauen nowe for to attayne</l>
               <l>Ye muſt apply to vertuous gouernaunce</l>
               <l>Ye in this worlde muſt yet take a payne</l>
               <l>Ye muſt not folowe your ſenſuall pleaſaunce</l>
               <l>Ye ſholde your ende haue in remembraunce</l>
               <l>Ye muſt forgyue as you wolde haue forgyuenes</l>
               <l>Ye than ſhall come to the glory that is endles.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:22708:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Alas theſe prouerbes, whiche I haue you tolde</l>
               <l>I lytell regarded in the tyme ſo paſt</l>
               <l>But nowe by reaſon I do them beholde</l>
               <l>Full well is hym that may haue grace <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loſt</l>
               <l>Beware ryght well, ſpende not your youth in waſt</l>
               <l>Leſe no tyme, but ſpende it vertuouſly</l>
               <l>Than ſhall ye come to hea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en merely.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ I wretched mayde plouged all in care</l>
               <l>The tyme ſo paſt may ryght ſore bewayle</l>
               <l>That the fleſſhe with ſlouth had me in a ſnare</l>
               <l>Alas the Deuyll dyd me ryght ſore aſſayle</l>
               <l>The worlde alſo dyd gyue me a battayle</l>
               <l>Theſe thre me fettered in a deadly place</l>
               <l>Tyll I was helpt out by good dame grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Whiche me hath ſet in his garden grene</l>
               <l>Vnder this olyue tree to ſynge ryght ſwetely</l>
               <l>Amyddes this arber ſo ryght fayre and ſhene</l>
               <l>Gyuynge great lawdes vnto God almyghty</l>
               <l>Whiche me hath brought out of vayneglory</l>
               <l>And there with all ſhe beganne to ſynge</l>
               <l>Lawdes to her maker in the fayre mornynge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ The cocke crowed and I dyd awake</l>
               <l>Greatly muſynge vpon my vyſyon</l>
               <l>And vnto me I brefly began to take</l>
               <l>Penne and ynke for to wryte that ſeaſon</l>
               <l>All that I had harde without abuſyon</l>
               <l>Preyenge you all that it doth here or ſe</l>
               <l>To Pardon me of your benygnyte.</l>
            </lg>
            <byline>¶ Finis. ꝙ Robert Wyer.</byline>
            <pb facs="tcp:22708:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
